should you go to college whether you are
young or old the decision to go to
college is a huge one I already did a
video on whether you should go to
college or not um the answer is probably
yes particularly in America and in
Europe it's free right but in America
you have to weigh the cost benefit and
all of that um but there there's really
five reasons to go to college and the
truth is if you can
accomplish those things if you can do
those things that you get from college
in other ways and I'm going to share a
couple stories of people who have done
this then I don't think college is as
required and I'm not the only one saying
that there are a lot of people who not
just old people but young people who are
now saying I don't need to go into
massive debt in order to accomplish
those five things so what are those five
things we are going to do htl CSS yes so
what are the five things the first thing
is obviously people go to college
to get a job now now that doesn't
necessarily that's not usually the first
reason to go to college that people go
they don't even think of that and
usually they'll pick a major like
psychology which I actually helped
someone actually get a job after they
got a major in Psychology because they
couldn't get work um I'm not bagging on
psychologist I'm just saying that if you
want a job you got to get a degree
that's going to get you a job I have a
Russian degree I actually had a job in
Russia but my wife told me she didn't
want to be in Russia anymore so I had to
Res skill and I had to use a bunch of
the things that I learned on my own uh
in the computer lab as a as a linguist
in linguis computer lab and also by
building out my own home lab without
going to college at all and continuing
to go to college so so that so the
number one reason is to get a job right
now you can definitely qualify you can
learn the skills to get a job without
going to college in fact I made a whole
video about why computer science might
not be the right choice for you computer
science is definitely the right choice
for certain professions but not the ones
you think if you want to work for a
silic and Valley or any company that's
doing things that's going to pay you a
tech salary you're probably not going to
want a computer science degree honestly
you're probably going to want uh the
skills that you would get shooting to
get a certification like a red hat
certification or one of these others now
there's another video of me drinking
while talking about the redhead
certification um because I really hate
that the system and compta and all the
CTS that are out there that that um you
can get to supplement your college some
of them are cheaper than that um they're
also not necessary to get a job and so
another story um some time ago I believe
it was in 2013 IBM made a very public
statement about that they don't require
anybody to have a college degree and
they made a big deal of it and they they
showcased a few people one of whom got a
security job for IBM uh at 18 without
having any anything all they had a lot
of they had a lot of knowledge I think
that person may have actually had a
security certificate of some kind but
the point that IBM was making and many
other big companies did around 2013 2014
that was a long time ago was that you
didn't need college and there's been
overwhelming evidence that um that you
still need to go to college to get a job
which brings us to the second point
right so IBM created a system called K
through 16 which was this educational
system that took you all the way through
the first couple you know years of
college and then you just would go
through that and then you would uh and I
don't even know where that landed I
don't know if you know if they're still
doing it but the the second main reason
to go to college is to get a job I mean
is to actually make more money at your
job and that is statistically borne out
by the science I'm going to refer to
Adam ruins College please go watch the
video about this it talks about yes at
every stage in their careers people that
went to college made 30% more in America
and um generally you know enjoyed better
opportunities because they went to
college I hate reporting that statistic
I hate it because it does shouldn't make
any difference if you have the skill you
should be paid for that skill the end um
and so that's that's the second reason
to make more money to get a job and to
make more money right those are not the
first two reasons that people s to go to
college most of them they said well they
want the third one which is to find
yourself to discover what it is you want
to be to you know to to you know smell
the roses and and figure out what it
means to be a thinker to take philosophy
classes to to you know get high or get
drunk and and figure things out or to
write poetry or to do whatever people
use College as an opportunity of
self-discovery and it's very expensive
to do that to go to college to to to pay
you know 3,000 $4,000 a semester to find
yourself it's an extremely expensive way
to do that take a gap year in fact some
colleges that are more responsible than
others have gone so far as to say you
can take a gap here and we will pay you
a scholarship for you to take a gap year
before College even starts so you can
figure it out what you want to be who
you are what you believe you know people
there's huge debate in in the in the you
know larger culture world world about
the value of a college education
particularly now in 2024 when there's
like all kinds of of radical you know uh
things happening on college campuses
because college campuses have
traditionally been the places where
progress happens that's where people are
testing the boundaries they're testing
their personal boundaries they're
testing their societal boundaries and
they're discovering things and some
people would say that that's the number
one reason to go to college that that's
why we have to have colleges we have to
have places where people can go and
think and and not care you know not care
about the bill that they're going to get
or the fact that they might lose their
job 10e professorships is one of the
worst things that ever happened in the
world because these people don't have to
worry about accountability at all
because they have a job no matter what
when is that ever a good idea I mean I
don't think that's a good idea anyway so
finding yourself who you want to be what
is your career going to be what are you
going to do with your life that is the
the third reason that's usually one of
the main reasons people go and along
with that who are you going to meet
along the way and this includes your
potential you know life partner uh
particularly Mormon if you're a Mormon
there was a joke a running joke saying
if you're a Mormon you're going to go to
college because that's where you're
going to meet your spouse right and so
women who are not encouraged to get
education were you know that they would
go there to find a husband they'd find
their husband they' drop out of school
and then they'd go back later in life it
was absolutely abysmally bad as horrible
thing because because you know education
for women is kind of downplayed and
they've since kind of come around on
that but the point is connections right
you're going to college to create
connections some of those connections
are going to be lifelong friendships
some of them are going to be potential
job opportunities some of them are I
mean professors right um some of the
some of the friendships that I have made
with professors while I was in college
have gone on to be some of the most
valuable things in my entire life and I
I cannot say it any way um and you know
some of the people that I met in college
they same sort of thing of course I met
my wife in college um so the people that
you meet in college are going to be the
some of the most important people you're
ever going to meet um again it's a very
expensive way to meet people and I'm
going to come back to that point what by
telling some stories about alternative
ways to do these different things and
the fifth thing is um to learn how to do
your
laundry to put it to put it bluntly
you've got to to learn how to adult
you've got to be a grown-up you've got
to take care of your laundry You'
whether you decide to live in your car
or an apartment or whatever you got to
learn to do your dishes uh whether it's
you only have one fork one knife and one
spoon so that you never have dishes pile
up like I had to do because if I
otherwise nobody would ever do the dises
you you've got to learn to get along
with people that your roommates with you
have to be a grown-up you have to learn
how to manage your life you got to do
your finances you have to understand
what it means to to to to to buy
something that buy your first computer
on credit so that you can build your
credit in America so that you can
survive in America because you have to
have credit you know there's a professor
a good friend of ours who went her whole
life without buying anything on credit
and she can't she can't do anything she
almost couldn't get a mortgage because
because she was so responsible with her
money the whole time because she's not
playing by the capitalist system I don't
care if you like it or not I hate it
that's just those are the rules of the
game so knowing the rules is is half the
battle so um let's talk about some
alternatives to doing those five things
so to to conclude primarily before we go
out to that to the next part it's really
important that you say uh to yourself
okay college is has become the most
convenient for many people it I'll be it
expensive college is the most convenient
way to do all five of those things right
they've got a dorm set up for you to
help you learn how to adult you know
they've got resident assistance to help
you know where to go get your
vaccinations when you need it I mean
they they got all kinds of weird things
there college campuses since the dawn of
time since the dawn of college campuses
have been set up to meet the needs of
those five things and it's extremely
convenient for most people it's also
very very expensive but why would you
need why would knowing about those five
things on their own be relevant okay so
let's give you a couple examples one of
them is getting getting the skills to
get a job and getting more to get a job
getting the credentials that are going
to get you money to get the job and
maybe meeting people that would get you
a job right let's talk about those three
things there's other videos on this but
let's say I'll do another video on
online universities right but when you
talk about a college experience the the
general college experience I went to
football games I had all the thing is
that you're you know it it's the
opposite of an online degree if you go
if you go get an online degree from an
accredited institution like WGU and
there's a separate video on that
then you are not having many of those
five experiences right but you're
spending a lot less money so one of the
ways to do the first three the the the
make more money and the get a skill job
skills and meet people going to get you
a job is to go to an online university
and or which is way way way cheaper or
focus on getting credentials or doing
whatever else it takes to established
trust that you can do the job those are
things you can do on your own if you
took the cost this is a true story so my
son um went to a community college uh
computer science 101 course and there's
about 85 people in the room or something
and they they asked him to raise his
hand and they said does anybody here
have any programming experience and he
raised his hand because he had already
completely learned how to code in Python
and go he'd made several applications in
in go um on the back end and then
actually JavaScript as well so I mean he
knew how to code he had proven he had he
had he had built online interactive
websockets based games
with all of the components of of
programming in that realm so he had a
lot of the I mean the fundamentals of
programming that were taught in cs101 he
had a lot of them and then he proceeded
to raised his hand he was the only kid
in the class who raised his hand he went
up and talked to his professor at the be
at the end and said is there any way I
can test out of this class and they said
no I'm sorry so he paid
$2,000 for a course that covered
material here had I have another story
about this Gabe if Gabe out there Gabe
taught himself assembly when he was 16
he ordered his own circuit boards that
arrived via DHL from China that he
designed On Solid Works himself while he
was with me while he was doing beginner
boo stuff he literally had his pick of
colleges and when he went to his first
college he had to take CS whatever to
teach computer to learn computer
engineering and he ended up teaching the
assembly class he paid $2,000 for the
privilege of being the unpaid ta for
that course
and then he immediately became the TA he
applied to be the TA and he became the
TA next he became the TA for the course
and now he's teaching all the play he
was in the class he knew everything he
knew everything in the course and he was
totally frustrated but he's like
whatever he paid all this money because
the system wasn't set up to let him say
oh I already know this right so there's
there's a couple of takeaways from that
the first one is you can learn any skill
that's taught in college you can learn
any skill that will get you in fact some
skills they won't teach in college many
MIT very famously has a thing called The
The Lost semester where they teach you
how to use desktop Linux among other
things because it's not included as a
part of the curriculum because it's not
serious enough you know it's totally
stupid and the point is is that you can
learn those skills other ways you can
make more relationships with other
people in other ways and you can do it
for on the cheap way better so WG is
another one of these universities where
you can learn all those things now WGU
is going to leave you hanging on the
other two things you're not going to
meet as many people through WGU bottom
line just not happening it's not going
to be as societ you're not probably not
going to meet your spouse at WGU right
you might you might make a business
contact or two but probably not so that
means you're going to need to actively
go out to meetups and do the things that
you have to do throughout your career
anyway might as well get started before
College in fact one of the biggest
complaints I have about college is that
because it so conveniently covers all
five of those things when people leave
College they don't know how to do those
things outside of college but if you
focus on preparing relationships at
local meetups knowing what conferences
to go to you know knowing who to hang
out with building a group of
professional peers and Friends reallying
a professional Learning Network if
you're doing those things which you
should be doing already then you've
already learned the skill now you're
just using the same skill and you
haven't had to pay any money to college
to learn it you haven't become dependent
on the college to cover them I mean and
the colleges have an entire ecosystem of
depend
because they they keep pumping in the
whole alumni thing give us more money
come back as an Alum help other people
who go to this college because you like
our College better than all the other
colleges
right no that I think it's a I think
it's a mistake for many people so those
are the five things so if you go to ww
how are you going to meet those other
two needs learning how to do your own
laundry and um what was the other one
making more money throughout your career
uh meeting other people I think the
learning how to adult is is the thing
the best way to do that and I'm going to
share a story here the best way to learn
how to adult and to meet other people
and oh no discover yourself discover who
you want to be so I have a I have a
story um I have a story from somebody
that is indirect that I read some time
ago it was about a woman who went to
college she went to Harvard she
graduated in Harvard and I don't
remember her degree and she wrote a an
article uh I believe it's on medium that
said every the most important things I
learned I didn't learn from college and
and it's pretty much the summary of it
is she went europ packing she went you
know backpacking in Europe and living on
the total Chap and she just accounts she
just recounts all of the really
life-changing experiences that happened
to her while she was just walking around
Europe meeting different people staying
in hosts getting to know you know you
know others and also thinking about what
she wanted to be who she was going to be
what she was going to do with her life
having a lot of time to think and Stu
some people do Appalachian trails some
people live out of their car and travel
across the country you know there there
are lots of opportunities to discover
yourself that do not have college in
fact I would suggest that college is
probably one of the worst places for you
to discover yourself it's a great it's a
great place to be exposed to new ideas
ideas that you might not have been
exposed to because you didn't know about
that book or you didn't know who Joseph
Campbell was or you didn't know I mean
there's a million things that you may
not have known but if you learn early
maybe after watching this video that you
can build yourself an autodidactic
learning plan that includes reading and
learning about the things that
constitute the bulk of self-discovery at
College you can do it you can make your
own self-discovery course or your own
thing and it can include interactions
with others it can include traveling the
world and it's going to be way way way
cheaper than a study abroad story about
that when I did study abroad I was like
I don't have the money I was working
thir three jobs to get myself through
college and this was in the 90s I don't
know how people go to college now right
and I was working three jobs I was like
I don't have money to pay $4,000 to go
on a Russian study abroad so you know
what I
did I was like let me see if I can find
a job so I found a job I found and got a
job being an American being being a
Russian Cruise uh translator which I
later kept kept growing that job got a
lot of experience in Russia was one of
the most proficient Russian speakers in
my entire Russian Department because I
was making money working in Russia and I
didn't have to do a study abroad for
that so I got paid to go to Russia they
paid to go to Russia you know what a lot
of those people who did study abroad did
they would go to Russia and because they
didn't they you usually they weren't
paying themselves by the way there was
somebody else was paying they would go
to Russia they would they would go with
their their American roommate they would
travel around they' speak English the
whole time they wouldn't learn anything
so they would be four $4,000 lighter
they come back they didn't have any
Russian skill and they had no other
experiences to talk to speak of
meanwhile I had came came back and I had
a lot of real solid experience teaching
uh teaching people English teaching them
business skills um and and learning how
to do the the whole thing in general so
the point of it is if you're GNA if
you're going to be able to do this long
term you need to really have a plan and
that plan should include um
self-discovery at a regular time you
don't need college for that and and
whatever techniques you learn to to find
yourself whether it's yoga or going on a
bike trip you should be doing that
anyway right you should be learning
those skills anyway so so don't you
don't necessarily have to go to college
for that if even if you do go to college
figure out what that is I don't need a
field trip in my Russian honors class to
show me Arch's National Park so that I
can basically get Mormon stoned and
recite poetry under an arch in southern
Utah I can do that all on my own I don't
need to pay money for that right so so
that's that's what I would suggest um
and hopefully that's been a summary of
whether you should go to college or not
and what are some of the things if you
if you're really trying this is a really
tough decision and the decision about
whether to go to college or not is
fundamentally colored by those by things
go ahead and review those for yourself
and let me know what you think put it in
the comments um that's just that's just
you know my idea that i' that I've had
with others that we' as we've talked
about whether they should go or not and
I do think that most people should get a
college degree um and I'll do another
video on that about how to get the
college degree as cheap as possible um
if if if that works for you and your
career plan and you should have that
plan before you even think about going
to college I know it's crazy can you
imagine actually knowing what you want
to be in life before you go to college
it can be done I've seen it